Castilian sounds if I direct one
research that studies how the
brain communicates with the body when
we meditate
Hello Nazareth, my name is Nerea, I am the mother of
two children of eight and ten years old I am
delighted to be here with you today
talking about such a fascinating and so
unknown to the ordinary citizen
What is the brain like? Physical actors are
PhD in neuroscience
you are conducting research on
the brain I die because we
explain what the brain is like and really
what it does
Well, thank you for seeing me, I am here.
Glad to be here with you if
Do you want to start by seeing what it is like?
brain let's imagine don't imagine
that we are flying over a forest that
we go on a plane and we go look there
downwards we do not imagine by the
Amazons, we are going to a forest, very well they are
very leafy if we see it from
Above what we see is a mass of vegetation
which seems to us to be a continuum
almost like a lawn, but very
complex and this is a debate that there was
well then
1905 approximately where it was thought
that our brain was a mass
continued it was as if we had
that forest from above where it was a
fabric that was so to speak smooth, this
It was what was called the theory
But at that moment a genius emerged
who is Don Santiago Ramón y Cajal, one of
our great sages who thought that
That was really a forest that
It was made up of units and he had
the idea that this forest was made up
by components that today
We know what neurons are if we
We see that forest from above because
Indeed we see that it is all a
Ramón y Cajal then continued, who was
an absolute genius came up with the idea of studying
a forest that was young instead of
study a brain that is already a brain
mature where the forest has grown
much said let's study a brain
embryonic, that is, a brain where
the trees are still growing and it is
thanks to that idea that Cajal had where
We begin to see what the theory is today
It is accepted that it is the neuronal theory that
Our brain is made up of some
components that are cells
nerves that are called neurons that
It is so to speak as if they were the
trees within our forest
neuronal a tree just like a neuron
has a body is what we
we call the soma where its
gender component where all of your work takes place
intrinsic activity but like
a tree our neurons have a
bad cup and have branches and have roots
how important what was highlighted is
Ramón y Cajal constantly is that
Although our brain is made up of
neurons the fundamental thing about the brain is
that these neurons communicate with each other
our neurons receive and send
information between them and thanks to that
is how information is transmitted by
the brain our neurons that
We imagined it was that tree again
Imagine then that tree and the body
neuronal is being charged with electricity
it's loading it's loading it's going away
loading and when reaching a certain
level of electricity as it emits a
electric shot and at that moment the
neuron the trunk the neuronal body by
its roots as if it were a cable
transmits electricity and it is
transmits to another neuron the other neuron
receives it by the cup by the branches in
the moment the electricity goes out
propagating through the cable that are the
roots the neuron that has that branch
receiver suddenly you receive a shot
of electricity and that moment that union
between the root of the neuron that has just
shoot and branch the neuron
receiver this this position this is
called the neuronal synapse since it happens
One thing that is very beautiful is that
when the neuron has just fired and
transmits electricity through that cable
some gates open on the cable and
neurotransmitters are released that
These are the chemical bases of
thought I always say that they are like
the letters that neurons send each other
with each other and this is the basic principle
of how our work
neurons transmit electricity from each other
the pulse is transmitted to each other
electric and then packages are sent
information that are like hormones
to each other then so that we
we can make complexes like for example
that I can be counting text now
that you are listening to me there are thousands of
neurons doing this communicating
sending electricity and sending itself
messages to coordinate an activity
that is so so important we are not
Speaking of a neuron, two neurons nor
ten neurons beat that our brain
has 86 billion neurons when
we study what the brain does when
we are doing something we are not talking about
individual neurons when we measure the
behavior neuroscience that
studies the behavior that studies
This is what groups of millions of people do.
neurons and that's where we already talked about
brain regions
for example he taught it to you in the brain
This brain, as I tell you, is noticeable
It weighs a kilo and a bit, every time I see it
I teach Shakespeare, it has been very gray
small you can say because it is that small
little when we study what
what the brain does when we are
memorizing when we are remembering
when we are doing anything
We already talked about areas of the
brain we always talk about the part of the
brain that is most involved in that
function because today we already know the
brain is an absolutely in system
network then connects what is very
nice to see in all that is the theory
neuronal perception is that when
We receive information, imagine
Now you're listening to me, ours is coming
brain has its receptors of the
senses for example hearing
information comes from outside
receivers translate into the world
biological language which is the
electricity and through your nerves
Well, they pass it on to the brain in the brain
the information follows a very long path
It is important to know that nothing happens
instant form but the
information for example those waves
sounds that are reaching you
time they pass from your brain to your body
They go through different stations and
There is a time between my word being
reached your ears and you are aware
What I'm saying is the first thing
What happens is in the deeper areas
of the brain there is a large receptor that
is the one who distributes the
information and says you come from the
ears then after some information
auditory you come from the eyes is a
visual information then the first thing
what is done is to recognize the words
memory then the emotional content
then the expression that is given to
our body how we react to it
that we are perceiving and then there is already
certain areas that translate it as
send to the superficial part of the
brain which is what we call
the bark only when the bark of the
brain is active that information is
aware of what that means, that great
part of our brain is dedicated
information that is not aware of
which we are not aware of
once the brain has passed through
different stations where I recognize the
I give it emotional content, I see
How the body reacts I translate it into
conscious and integral all this
information because it reaches me because
that's like a puzzle and in the end all that
I associate the whole until they are
aware of what I am experiencing
Now at that moment, look at the
final as it is from that little one
neuron that is collecting information
passing electricity on that road
of nerves, not of roots and branches
that are communicating with each other or with dad
how all that is happening until
final and a coordination of millions and
millions and millions of neurons that
make it possible for us to be able to
perceive as a mother of two girls many
Sometimes I worry about being able to help them
in your emotional management
especially so that their own
new emotions overflow into life
but it is very complicated because their children
They don't control their reactions as you think
that I could help them because I am mine too
I have a girl like you who has two selves
I have a girl and I had this
studying what the neuroscience of the
emotions of well-being and so that everything
the process of motherhood I have seen that
It's true that I hadn't learned much.
I faced then seeing attacks of anger in
my impatience
loss of control and managing fatigue
also because a love has been felt that
I had never felt a commitment
learned a lot and I think that
motherhood or fatherhood is usually with
children are the episode of life
where we could say we learn the most
together then I continue because yes I
considers myself a mom's apprentice because I
I make a lot of mistakes, I think I really like a
field of research that he leads on
every israeli who speaks of what is
physiological coherence where it says that the
transmission from parents to children
especially from the mother
Children go far beyond the word
from the expression that the systems
endocrine are correlated
brains and hearts you know that
when we see our children in a
coherence a synchronization with these
hearts that is very beautiful and that to
me that led me to think then to try
to establish or cultivate in me the change that
I would like it for my son then
There are many management techniques
emotions that are very interesting already
I really like one in particular that
is being very avant-garde in the
neuroscience which is using the body
because because when we notice that
We have said before that the brain when
We receive the information through
example we hear something is not
instant I think it is instant
because I just perceived I just
listen to you and I think it just arrived
but that information takes a while to
things are not processed in the brain
they instantly make emotions
They also take time to prepare
in the brain but what happens that that
preparing their potential
preparatory that preparation of the
excitement is brewing it is brewing
cooking an emotion in me
but it is being cooked in a way that is
not conscious then how can I
know what is being prepared how
can I know something be aware of
something that is still being
unconscious because within all that
a journey that generates emotions
by our our brain one of the
first stations through which the
emotion is a brain station that
coordinates the body's response and
my body's response to that emotion
It is prior to the conscious moment in which
that I perceive that emotion
So this is why it is said that the
body knows what the mind has not yet known
realized is the somatic marker
so if we what the says
scientific literature is if we
we have body awareness
I can observe in my body what is
is being prepared before it has already been
expressed emotion when I have that
consciousness or saying that one is
preparing one is better than best
the one we live is better that I put myself
Let's get to work because a good one is coming
an ingredient that I would highlight more in
the polite thing is to work more with the
expression of one's own body that from
small children learn to recognize
the emotions in your body that you learn
to have body awareness where it is
the joy where you feel it where it is
anger then you learn to
identify and then you recognize in
your own body sensations that you already have
They warn me that today I am starting to
put like this or put like this that the child
learn to recognize your posture that the
child learns to educate his own posture
that the child learns to relate to
his own body said William James no
I cry because I'm sad I'm sad
because I cry if the sensations of your
body emotion would be a notion
abstract only an intellectual concept
I'm nervous no
you have to feel it in your body
I think that for example and I love it
what is happening now
neuroscience which is the neuroscience that
It encompasses the entire body because it always
We associate everything with the brain and we take care of it
mental health brain the brain the
intelligence the brain the emotion but
It has been seen that if you do not communicate with the
heart we do not perceive what is happening
out without interaction with the
intestine because it does not regulate well all
our social properties our
behavior
breathing with the nose is accentuated
our care mechanisms our
brain interprets
constantly the posture of our
body, that is, the posture we have
posture of our body is fundamental
for our brain to know how we are
our is constantly interpreted
body today because we know that it is
does physical exercise that is another
something that we always think about, for example
that physical exercise is good for the
health is good at the cardiovascular level is
Good for immune level, physical exercise
It is a great protector of mental health
you are also exercising for your
brain because it has been seen that when
we do exercise is more cardiovascular
In this case the hippocampus which is a
structure that is shaped like a little horse
of the sea is the part of the brain most
important for memory because when
we exercise the hippocampus becomes
stronger neural forest than
inhabits the hippocampus
and that is a great protector but on the other hand
part has been seen that for example
practice yoga practice tai chi chi
kung or for example among others
expression exercises that involve
body awareness
It strengthens the brain then for me
major would be happy in education from
little ones and more that will be jon or that
Since I was little they would have taught me to
recognize the expression of my body
take better care of my body posture
brain we are born with has us
fully
default is possible
to work individually in a
conscious even to change your
personality if you know who you are then
I am not a very shy person and you
would like to be more extroverted or if you are
pessimistic and wants to be more optimistic is
It is possible to work on that respect, because look
That's very nice because I think there is
that recognizing this complexity must be
Recognizing the difficulty I think does
damage to treat it from a point of view
superficial and with excessive optimism in
that sense but there is also that
recognize that we can do it and that the
brain is much more grateful than
that we think for example it has been seen that
when we started meditating at 5 days
we begin to see changes in our
brain or it is difficult for the time
Ramón y Cajal is very grateful that, as
We said, because he is one of the fathers of the
neuroscience I would dare to say
as a tribute to him because not only
discovered what architecture is like
neuronal but he also discovered
something called brain plasticity
There is a phrase of his that seems to me that
It summarizes very well what he wanted
express he said every man can be
if he proposes it as a sculptor of his own
brain in neuroscience we study
especially what the clay is like
the brain is made of and what its
habits how it works how it is transmitted
electricity what are its
mechanisms our brain has a
activity that is spontaneous and we
we measure that and it is more and the activity
spontaneous brain that provides
our our mind or our
experiences our mental states
of a capacity that is involuntary that
It is spontaneous, many things arise
times when we want it
voluntarily but on the other hand today
Today we are also dealing with what
is the sculptor is that ability that
have
voluntarily with our intention
our purpose as you say
which is another of our greats
neuroscientists as with the purpose
with intention we can
By sculpting we can change our brain
So it's always a game in the end.
between the clay and the sculptor then
one of the questions that is always asked
which is now studied from the point of view of
academic view is valid then in that
I play in that fight or in that dance
Between clay and the sculptor what can we do?
do how we can do it one of the
main properties that have the
clay is the habits when our
brain gets used to something is very
difficult to get him out of there later because
because of all the options that
always has to go to that one in the
who is more accustomed then to
the whole range of possibilities that
The brain says which one I choose.
choose that option from the fan
that is stronger in the brain is
say that it has been used more times
The Greeks always said I am not
as I am but as I am used to being
and that's a bit what happens in the brain
then one of the big questions to
It seems to me that it is in the field of neuroscience
and here it is mainly led by
Cambridge University is worth zero
He is used to doing this and I know that
This for example is harmful to me
There is a habit that is harmful to me
so many times we focus on
I don't have to say this but
as long as you don't tell the brain how
I would have to do it, it will continue
doing it
that is to say
and doing it in a way that doesn't give you options
try to inhibit a behavior
reinforce this is impressive it is not
demonstrates once in a study that
I started fabulous try not to do no
do this don't do this don't think
Come on, don't think for your brain
fixing it our brain does not know
forget we all know how
learn truth we have studied then
okay I repeat over and over again a thousand times and
I'm left with it, we know how to remember
Now how do we forget, imagine?
for example that I know you and tips
Nerea, okay, that way it goes, way to go
Nerea has repeated it to me three or four times.
times and I stay and I work with you
imagine yourself daily and I already know that you
you call Nerea then for Massalín
instantly and you arrive one day from bc
No, they don't call me r anymore, now I call myself
white and then take and then my
brain every time I see you at first
What is going to happen if you call NBA because
because that is the strongest circuit
so our brain doesn't know how to forget
knows how to replace then every time my
brain I see you and say your name is Nerea
I consciously with the intention with
the purpose and is not called white
then they call us ere a thousand times a thousand
sometimes after two or three weeks already
in Nerea's neural circuit and the
white neural circuit weighs the same
for the brain, competition for breakfast
So who tips the scales?
towards one habit or another
intention the purpose and that is the
voluntary control but for that, look
I have to observe myself, I observe myself
what has come out of me to say Mary observed it
I realize and voluntarily with my
intention support the other when the
white circuit weighs more than that of
Nerea the brain is very beautiful replaces
and this one leaves then I no longer
I'll remember that your name is Media then
how we change a habit
automatic versus another replace it
but to replace what I have to
to do is to have the purpose to have that
intention that is what the tells us
literature one of the studies that well
It seems more interesting, more beautiful
what did the University of England do?
next to Washington is the one who demonstrated
A survey was conducted asking the
People, you are generous in itself.
altruistic, not much like most people
of people is how I am not generous is
As if they would not continue, then I am there.
I'm like that, that's it, I don't need one
Well, experiment, let's try it.
that during this month he grants us a month
where you
will voluntarily choose to be generous
So let's see if anything changes.
So you think that changing is not possible?
because I am not what she said
majority then what was seen is that
even optimism and generosity were
something that could be grown I like
much the word cultivate why why
that cultivating does not mean generating
To cultivate means that you sow there
times that something will not be born because it is not
I think everything depends on us
but I think that cultivating it is very
we probably have it
then it would be that optimism would
could be cultivated that the
generosity could be cultivated that the
people who had chosen
voluntarily
be more generous during that time
had had changes in their brain in
certain areas that correlated with
an improvement in their level of well-being
people felt happier who
had fostered optimism because
had also had changes in a
brain structure that is the cortex
orbitofrontal which is like the one that is
above the eye socket is
a key area to protect ourselves from
I recognize that there are anxiety states
a feeling I have with great
frequency which is like
because the feeling of not being able to stop
that you have a thousand things on your mind at the same time
Maybe you go with 200 topics in parallel and at the same time
In the end you reach a point where you don't
you concentrate on none that pass from
brain when you are like this because many
Sometimes we get into a lot more things than
the ones we can do when you lose and it happens to you
To you who sometimes complain is tired
This is that he couldn't take it anymore and then
Of course I accept many more challenges.
of those that maybe I could and I like
Give me a phrase that I think should be
Hippocrates did not say what he said before healing
Someone ask him if he is willing to
give up what makes you sick
I think that many times we don't want to
give up many things the price that
we pay is an immense tiredness already
sometimes not always the best expression
emotional towards those who hate us but
On the other hand, it is true that today
everything is going very fast because we have
a lot of work and there are children who
in the distances in the cities are
very long, that is to say that we have then
many many many work in many
tasks throughout the day and it is normal
that we are tired one of the things
that has been seen in the literature that
that tire us more or overwhelm us and
It is more stressful to be doing one thing and
thinking I have to make five thousand more
that this is what I think is happening to us.
Here I am thinking, I have it here, no
I know I haven't answered this, that is to say
that you are in one place but you are in another
There is a study that was published in the year
2012 which he did at the University of
Harvard very interesting that showed
note that 47 percent of the time
that we are awake or that is
practically half of the day we are
in doing one thing and our mind in
On the other hand, Harvard called this work
a wandering mind is an unhappy mind
because what they saw is that
when we are doing one thing but it
we are doing but my mind is on
on the other hand, what was this is a
unpleasant is something that we do not
like or is something that is uncomfortable if you
we are doing and our mind is
here and there thinking about five thousand
things that are said out there wandering around
Well, that becomes a little more
dislikes
if what we are doing in principle
It was neither here nor there, neither pleasant nor
unpleasant but I am the action of
my mind is elsewhere it becomes a
a little more unpleasant and if we were
doing something that was originally
pleasant but my mind is wandering
from one side to the other it transforms into
Something less pleasant is to say that
In the end, the best version was whatever you do.
do it do it no and that's why here we are
I brought something that we have said to the
throughout history when returning to the
present, that is to say, there is no need to be there
24 hours is true that this capacity of
anticipating and predicting helps us a lot
But what the studies do say is that
you have to reduce it a little more, right?
we can be there half the day
doing one thing and our mind in
another you have to spend more time doing
whatever we are doing, there is a
study at Harvard University in
He seemed to be very surprising.
It is true that it was very revolutionary.
publishes in the journal Science them
They say an experiment where they carried out
people to the laboratory and were asked to
for a while as long as they
would like to try to control
voluntarily his thoughts were
in a room where there was no
type of distraction there was a TV
There were magazines just for
favor and magic shooting nerea simply
stay for a while as long as you want
you want trying to control to see
where your mind goes try to control your
thoughts
Well, you know what the average time is.
that the people endured for six minutes and
that the researchers told the
statistic was that 83 percent of
people said that the experience
It had been very unpleasant
experiment was repeated up to five times
It was done by taking people to their
home because maybe the laboratory
It was very imposing and for example Cannes did
the experiment in people's homes
30 percent acknowledged that they had
hiding the mobile phone, that is to say, what
The study said that it is something that we have
read in all the literature throughout
of all history is that we do not know
be with ourselves who do not know
control our own mind that the
voluntary control of our mind is
something much more complex than what
we think
but if we don't know that it is complex and
if we don't know what it really means to us
a benefit to learn to be with
ourselves and learn to manage
our mind, well that takes us
always to that eternal combat and that is what
that you train a lot for example when
we practice mindfulness I'm going to
voluntarily practice being more
attentive to be doing what you are doing
doing and that according to what we
studies say it translates into greater
well-being above all in doing
understanding that if you learn to be in
the present
In the end he is much happier because
many times the stress and anxiety that
we have in the day to day comes
precisely because they are not able to stop
and focus attention on things but
what is in the brain what
occurs in the brain when it really
we managed to focus attention on something
Well, look, if you want, if you want, I'll give it to you.
I have the brain, let's go
imagine that we are doing a
exercise to practice being in
the present one of the practices then
that are most used by which
we started is for example imagine that
I'm telling you, we're going to be here for a moment
let's sit quietly and go
to simply be observing
how we breathe how / the air comes out through
your nose through your mouth what's going on in
your body is simply an exercise in
the one you
you voluntarily take the attention and
focus on the sensations of your
breathing something that we can
practice which is one of the practices
most common thing that is done there I like
much define how William James does the
attention as taking possession of the
mind he himself said that reality is
what I paid attention to
Many times when talking about the
Meditation is often said to be a
fashion which is a technique that comes then
mainly from the east but when
we talk about the attention of meditation
like that control that training of
our mind or attention is something
Well, it has been studied throughout the
history of humanity for example
we do not go further in our
Renaissance 'Luis Vives' was one of the
great experts, great scholars
of attention as that takeover
of your own mind meditation is in
all cultures not only in the East and
It's not something we've just invented.
and I say that because I don't believe it is
a fashion but rather a capacity
intrinsic that we have to
try to get to know each other and observe each other
ourselves then if you put yourself
to observe you say well everything disappears
I'll be there for a few minutes
I'm going to see how the air comes in and out
through my nose, what happens in the brain?
I'll tell you what would be
happening in your brain at that moment in
the one you are simply observing
the sensations of your breathing
brain is practically centered here
in the front of the brain
specifically an area that is the cortex
dorsolateral prefrontal no matter one
part here in the brain all the rest
I would be more or less quiet, that's why
He tells him that he is also a soldier in
neuronal silence is quiet
You're just there for this, it's very beautiful
because look, there are many times
compared to the frontal cortex as well as
to attention like the miner's lamp
You know that miners wore a helmet
that they had a light and then you only see
what they focus on only
exists is three at the time does not exist
nothing but the sensations of your
breathing then at that moment everything
your brain is practically focused on
This part of the brain that is the part
frontal part of the brain then we are there
for a little while
and not much because our ability to
attention is much more limited than
what we think
and then suddenly without you knowing it
you want to say
we unintentionally get distracted
you were distracted, you were watching for a while
as the air entered and left through your
nose and suddenly you remembered I don't know
what and now what do I have to say let's see and
what was next and then what
the brain that was passes at that moment
almost all quiet and only this part
front at that time has been filled with
colors
what we observe in the machine
It is an activity that exists here and
from there to here for an immense hustle and bustle
Tibetans, for example, call that
state the cage of the monkeys to which
he applies a scorpion to them and when I
when I saw him it was in the laboratory
when you see the images and it is that it is
literally this is what a cage looks like
monkeys because because suddenly I
I remember things, I imagine things came up
a lot of internal dialogue starts to
remember and here think about what I have
what to do next but all that is super
fast and then there you have abandoned the
voluntary control of your attention by
That is what meditation is said to be
combat between the volunteers in
will I want to be attending to
the sensations of my breathing and my
brain takes and has gone and thrown away
to that world of fantasies where one is
remembering things and imagining where it is
talking and all that without you having done it
chosen voluntarily
You spend some time there and suddenly you realize
realize that you have been distracted which
are the areas of the brain that occur
account and this is the most important part
from the neuroscience of meditation
identify the parts of the
brain that allows you to give yourself
realize that you have been distracted with me
distracted he had to be paying attention to
the sensations of breathing are
fundamental parts that are here
within the brain is the cortex
cingulate a kind of umbrella that
we have inside the brain which is the one that
the switch that goes from what
unconscious to conscious
that and an area of the brain that is the
insula which is the part of the brain that is the largest
involved in the idea of who I am
so when we are
By meditating we are controlling our
attention what we are doing is
train our brain to give itself
I realize myself, I realize myself
that distracts me as I realize when
that island, that idea of self and that cortex
cingulate to which it translates in
conscious and conscious joins and they
Two say and 15 I get distracted and I give myself
realize that I am like this once you
you have realized your own state already
the brain immediately asks
the memory areas and what we have
what to do and that's where the
purpose while you say had to
be paying attention to the sensations of the
breathing if we do this for a few
half an hour a day we train our
brain to the most present in a
thing in particular but above all there
we are in our brain to realize
of ourselves and this is not only
valid for learning to be in the
present but also I don't know for
learn to identify ourselves
Imagine yourself in a conflict
where we shoot where we start to
say things that may not be the case
more appropriate because there we do have
strengthened that network that tells you listen how
a kind of mirror doesn't hear that you are
So if you want to continue, it's fine, but
You better not want to continue and that is one of
the parts I think are the most important of
This whole field is not the
neuroscience meditation is what it is
you have seen is that when we started to
Practicing the frontal area strengthens the
cingulate cortex also grows
insula grows the amygdala which is an area
of the brain that is most involved in
the emotions at best of a character
more negative
decreases that is correlated with
a lower feeling of stress
feeling of anxiety, that is to say that as
You see our brain is very plastic and
Furthermore, what has been seen is that it does not do
you need to be a great meditator and meditate
eight hours a day or live in a
monastery but to meditate and practice the
attention half an hour a day is already
produce changes in the brain in what
relating to the children who came
talking
They should start meditating, it would help them
something is an exercise that one goes to
start at a later adult age
conscious
Well, I think that meditation helps me
I would be left with the aspect that is meditating
it's a bit of getting to know yourself
that the Tibetans the room that
They use to meditate that the bomb is
the origin of the word one of them is
where you become familiar, that is to say, it is the
moment in which you start to
observe your breathing or your
thoughts emotions your states
mental in general and I think that is
one of the great tools that
we have at the level
psychological at a general mental level is
say have accustomed to our
brain accustom us to giving
account of myself observing us
we ourselves have many exercises
that are done with children after observing
how her tummy goes up and down when
when they breathe for example at the end and
cape is just an exercise to say
Look at you, I think that education
Note that I tell you this because I have studied
many years and at some point
of my life of my career I'm angry with
the educational system, so to speak
studied many years to me nobody
He said he had to study me
that he had to know me, I think
that this although people later
we take for granted I think it should be done
We also have to be more explicit
that habit of observing ourselves
to know each other, to observe each other, to learn to
respecting each other then is something that I do
that would make it more explicit in teaching
and in your last book you make a simile that
I found it very beautiful between the rhythms
brain function and
composition of boleros
After explaining what it consists of,
look when I started my PhD
I was in a laboratory where they made
experiments on rats were put in
electrode and you could see what they were doing
neurons did not know a machine that
translated electricity into sound until
to Kiel and got used to working there
a little then our neurons
when they emit an electric shock
you know we have said the neuron was with
a kind of tree that has branches and
that has roots when the being the body
neuronal the trunk is loaded with
electricity
emits an electric shock that
we call post shots like that
These electrical discharges are emitted in
rhythms related to a bit like
percussionists then have
different ways of issuing I say that
neurons sing no more than they speak
They can do it very slowly
for example an electric shock by
the second can do it faster 4
can do it faster 8 downloads
electric currents per second
for example the most important rhythm of
our brain is alpha which is about eight
or ten electric shocks per second
but there are times when they can do it very
fast can reach up to 50 downloads
electrical per second for pa pa pa pa
pa pa pa pa pa pa and that is to say and those are
the languages they speak
when a neuron is emitting
electric discharges in alpha and another is
emitting electric discharges in alpha
They talk among themselves if one is in alpha and
the other is in beta as it is said in
another thing I can talk to this one in
rise and with the other in beta, that is to say
They have different trans languages
Lately multilinguals do not speak to each other
yes and those are their ways of communicating
They communicate with those who speak in
the same languages one of the
The most important languages are alpha
It is the rhythm, that is the fundamental rhythm
about 8 electric shocks from the brain
per second and alpha demonstrate the
University of Birmingham Ole Jensen what
is one of the great stieg adores
showed that the alpha rhythm is very
important for us to be able to
keep your attention because the rhythm
alpha emerge as if they were signals of
stop in our brain when we
people are paying attention to
something and I'm doing any kind of
thing for example now you are talking
with me we are listening to each other I myself
I imagine your brain is full now
of alpha waves because because our
brain begins to generate
internally a lot of interference
suddenly I remember I don't know what now
I have to go to I don't know what all those are
things that are interferences that come
from within and the interferences that
They come from within and are much more than the
that come from outside is then valid for
that you can be paying attention to what
We are currently going through the
brain has to be inhibiting the
others who are the inhibitors or
alpha waves then the brain
It starts to fill with alpha waves and it's like
if who makes the brain certain areas
of signs of this comes the
interference here and is found
with some neurons dad dad dad himself
emitting electric discharges in alpha
interference arrives and cannot pass
Okay, there is a barrier when we start to
Meditating increases alpha waves
so for example a person who
start meditating and still don't have
much control over your attention to the corporal
After meditating for a while, he already has many
alpha waves there then that allows you
maintain attention when we already have
control over our attention this is
very nice the alpha waves are withdrawing
signs of these are removed because they are no longer
interferences arise and it is no longer necessary
control then is the language that
they have neurons they don't have many
many functions but not only have
rhythms of our brain our heart
our breathing is also beating
cyclical our intestine also emits
an electric field that is also
cyclic goes very very slow 0.05 hertz
but the funny thing, the beautiful thing is that everyone
those cycles, all those rhythms of the body
They fit together when we
example that has been demonstrated in the
university of good with you are
paying attention to something there is a coupling
between the rate of increase and the rate of
heart if suddenly you are like this very
Be careful because I imagine there is a coupling
wonderful heart brain suddenly
you start to get bored, it starts to get distracted
begins to decouple, meaning that
In the end, that's why I didn't see it like that.
absolute great bolero that is ours
body with its different rhythms as
an impressive orchestra where
Well, there are times when it sounds good, there are times when it sounds good.
That sounds bad, who is the director then?
we don't know
easily
Food is another topic on the
that you work as a person and as
Mother seems very important to me because I
I think we all have it clear
impact of a diet
inadequate on our physical health
but what is the real relationship between what
what we eat and our brain well this
It is one of the not exciting topics of
This decade I always say that those of us
we dedicate ourselves to neuroscience at least I do
I feel absolutely privileged
because we are living in a moment that
It is very nice that it is a revolution
scientist 10-15 years ago and you said
that the rest of the organs had something
What do you have to do with the brain? I had no idea.
no sense was a bit crazy
but today we know that our
brain is communicating
constantly with the heart that
the way we breathe is fundamental
for our care mechanisms
memory the expression of emotions and
perhaps within that revolution the theme
which has been developed the most is the
influence that the intestine has on
the brain
It is known that the influence of the intestine
on the brain is greater than the
influence that the brain has on the
intestine that has been seen not through
anatomical pathways and functional studies
in three imagine that our intestine
We are all a vehicle of
millions and millions and millions of
microorganisms that live in us
which are mainly bacteria
mainly then 90% of all
the bugs that live in our body
They are in the intestine and this is what
we call the microbiota
intestinal microbiota that today
Well, the microbiota is often mentioned.
is that universe is the set of
microorganisms that live in the
intestine because it is influenced
mainly due to diet
physical exercise for relationships
social for the medicines for the
probiotics or prebiotics with the
pollution levels by the level of
stress about the way we have
born if necessary by part
then those little bugs that live
within us at first we
I thought that they were because they made us
damage then that which does not stop us from living
there and today we know that they are vital
vital for our endocrine system
that is, hormonal for our system
immune but also for our brain
It has been seen that the relationship
microbiota influence it has on
our brain influences the processes
learning
influences the mood in the
sense of humor in how we
we find influences attention
influences how we relate to others
other why because the influence that
has the intestine on the brain
when that influence reaches the brain
It mainly affects the areas of the
brain that we call the brain
social, that is to say, pay attention to what is important
which is, among other things, taking care of your diet
to take care of the relationships we have
among us there is a researcher in
Australia happiness here what is it
wonderful that I already know that she studies
direct relationship between diet and
behavior then she that has
done many longitudinal studies has
seen for example that the diet that takes
the mother during pregnancy
influences predicts with mathematical models
how the emotion regulation will be
of the child's behavior up to 5
years the diet that the child takes during
The early years are not only important
Well, at a nutritional level, as we know,
that influences the factors of
brain growth influences how
That child is going to live his emotions in the
mechanisms that your brain has to
learn how you will manage your
own behavior or that is to say that we
We are very concerned that the child knows
English so I know the other thing but how
I say and then we don't take care of the vehicle
Well, how are we going to get far?
I think that understanding that taking care of the body
It is also taking care of the mind is something that
It would be essential from a very young age in
Nazareth finally I would like to ask you
that you will share with us some
advice that allows us to take care of
our brain in everyday life
Well, look at one of the topics that I am most interested in.
I'm so busy lately with what
personal as well as professional is what it is
the neuroscience of being kind to yourself
same
maybe and this is to see what happens a
a little more in women according to what they say
studies sometimes we are very demanding and
very hard on ourselves, right?
be the best mom the best cat they say
the studies is that this hardness is
demand is not so efficient in the end and
in the end how to be kind to yourself
when our brain, well, we have a
conduct that is perhaps more than
scold us for demanding that we speak to each other
harshly this is reflected in some parts
of the brain are parts of the brain that
It has been seen that they are more associated with
generating stress is generating anxiety
when on the contrary I recognize the
weaknesses I recognize the problem but
I am kind to myself and that is not
It means not being ambitious and not wanting
improve but I do it from a deal
a little kinder more careful more
respectful and more compassionate with us
the same areas of the brain are other
when we criticize ourselves
zones that are also zones are activated
of pain but when that is activated
more friendly behavior
activate areas such as the cortex
orbitofrontal which are more related
with him with optimism with happiness
with well-being when we learn to be
kind to ourselves too
we learn to do with others
different this is something that comes out to us
in all experiments what
we carry out in the
laboratory and other literature in
general is that we study in the
laboratory how the body changes when
in people learn to change
attitude is not then one of the variables
that always comes out more important to us
from a statistical point of view it is
how their level of kindness has changed
with itself for example increases the
quality of sleep is a study that is
He did a 9-year study in Germany
where it was seen that fostering kindness
with oneself the quality of
sleep we already know that the quality of sleep
affects me then to be
aware of that more friendly treatment with
I myself believe that it is one of the greats
tools that we should promote
a little more and especially since very
little ones
Nazareth has been a very good place in many ways
pleasure to have this conversation so
interesting with you on a topic that
would remain for hours
Thank you very much Nerea, I was very happy
I am very happy and it is a pleasure thank you
[Music]